Guide to the Tommie L. Watkins Jr. papers, 2000-2005.
Watkins, Tommie L., Jr. papers, 2000-2005
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Tommie L. Watkins Jr. papers, 2000-2005.
7737
Tommie L. Watkins Jr.
0.3 cubic ft.
N/A
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers of Rev. Tommie Lee Watkins Jr., documenting his interaction with the U.S. Navy regarding their demand that he repay tuition. During the three-year administrative process, Watkins asserted that the Navy's insistence that he repay tuition when it had excused numerous cases involving white students was influenced by racism. His papers also document his views on communities of faith and the inclusion and affirmation of gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgender people, those questioning their sexuality, people living with AIDS, and their families. Includes correspondence, essays, clippings, and a videorecording of a service at Miami, Florida's Greater Bethel A.M.E. (African Methodist Episcopal Church) Church on April 15, 2001, where Watkins worked as program director for HIV/AIDS prevention education.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ordained a Baptist minister in 1991, Watkins served as youth minister at the First Missionary Baptist Church of Hueytown in Bessemer, Alabama. He attended the United States Naval Academy from 1994 to 1997, where he was elected class president and earned the rank of battalion commander. In 1997, he resigned after allegations of homosexual activity. He finished his degree at the Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University in Florida, and has worked as a business analyst, math teacher, and health educator focusing on gay youth and communities of color. In 2000, the South Florida Conference of the AME Church denied his application for ordination as an A.M.E. itinerent deacon (the lowest level of itinerent minister). He founded the Ministry of Reconciliation, which is an inclusive and affirming education and worship experience primarily for Black Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender, Questioning persons, Persons Living With AIDS (PLWAs), and their family members. In 2005, Watkins published a book about his life experiences titled "Living Out Loud."
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers of Rev. Tommie Lee Watkins Jr., documenting his interaction with the U.S. Navy regarding their demand that he repay tuition. During the three-year administrative process, Watkins asserted that the Navy's insistence that he repay tuition when it had excused numerous cases involving white students was influenced by racism. His papers also document his views on communities of faith and the inclusion and affirmation of gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgender people, those questioning their sexuality, people living with AIDS, and their families. Includes correspondence, essays, clippings, and a videorecording of a service at Miami, Florida's Greater Bethel A.M.E. (African Methodist Episcopal Church) Church on April 15, 2001, where Watkins worked as program director for HIV/AIDS prevention education.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Watkins, Tommie L., Jr.; African Methodist Episcopal Church--Florida.
Subjects:
African-American gays--United States.; Gay clergy--United States.; Homosexuality--Religious aspects.; Homophobia--United States.; Race discrimination--United States.
Places:
United States--Armed Forces--Gays--Government policy.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Collecting program: Human Sexuality Collection
CONTAINER LIST
- 2004 resume and Colin Higgins Courage Award certificate of recognition, Box 1, Folder 1 (Box 1)
- "Ministry of Reconciliation," paper by Watkins, 2000; Box 1, Folder 2 (Box 1)
- Correspondence re: debt to the Navy, 2000; Box 1, Folder 3 (Box 1)
- Henderson, Mitch letter to editor about Watkins' debt to Navy, Box 1, Folder 4 (Box 1)
- Washington Post, 2000; Box 1, Folder 5 (Box 1)
- "Rev. Tommy Watkins: Faith Warrior," article in Venus and readers' responses, 2001; Box 1, Folder 6 (Box 1)
- CU Out and About (Univ. of Colorado at Boulder), 2002; Box 1, Folder 7 (Box 1)
- Clippings, ca. 2000; Box 1, Folder 8 (Box 1)
- Clippings, 2000-2005; Box 1, Folder 9 (Box 1)
- Mosaic event poster, 2003; Box 1, Folder 10 (Box 1)
- Greater Bethel A.M.E. Church service, 2001; v. 722 (Box 1)
- Rev. Tommie Watkins Articles of Venus, 2001; Box 2, Folder 1 (Box 2)
- Advocate Article and Bulletin Full Truth Ministries, 2006; Box 2, Folder 2 (Box 2)
- Events, 2007; Box 2, Folder 3 (Box 2)
- Diplomas and Articles, 2008; Box 2, Folder 4 (Box 2)
- Diplomas, 2008; Box 2, Folder 5 (Box 2)
- Articles, 2009; Box 2, Folder 6 (Box 2)
- Articles, 2009; Box 2, Folder 7 (Box 2)